<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true and full relation of the horrible and hellish plot of the Iesuites Popish priests and other papists in Ireland, for the massacring of the two chiefe justices, and all the Privie Councell and Protestants in that kingdome. As it was related by my Lord Keeper in the house of Commons November the first. 1641.</title>
            <author>Littleton, Edward Littleton, Lord, 1589-1645.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94918</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T2481</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E173_15</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17725</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860254</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860254</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112371</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94918)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112371)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 30:E173[15])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true and full relation of the horrible and hellish plot of the Iesuites Popish priests and other papists in Ireland, for the massacring of the two chiefe justices, and all the Privie Councell and Protestants in that kingdome. As it was related by my Lord Keeper in the house of Commons November the first. 1641.</title>
                  <author>Littleton, Edward Littleton, Lord, 1589-1645.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Bankes, and are to be sold at his shop on Bridewell Stayers in Black-Fryers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ireland --  History --  Rebellion of 1641 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112371:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 36 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:112371:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 36 -->
            <p>A TRVE AND FVLL RELATION of the horrible and helliſh Plot of the Ieſuites Popiſh Prieſts and other Papiſts in <hi>Ireland,</hi> for the Maſſacring of the two chiefe Juſtices, and all the Privie Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell and Proteſtants in that Kingdome.</p>
            <p>As it was related by my Lord Keeper in the houſe of Commons <hi>November</hi> the firſt. 1641.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Bankes,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop on <hi>Bridewell ſtayers</hi> in <hi>Black-Fryers.</hi> 1641.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:112371:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 37 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:112371:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 37 -->
            <head>A True and full Relation of the horrible and helliſh plot of the Ieſuits Popiſh Prieſts and other Papiſts in <hi>Ireland,</hi> for the Maſſacring of the two cheife Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices, and all the Privie Councell and Proteſtants in that Kingdome.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Lord Keep<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r declared unto the Houſe of Commons, that the Lord Deputy of <hi>Ireland</hi> had received a Letter from the two Lord Cheife Iuſtices and Privie Counſell in <hi>Ireland,</hi> of the diſcovery of an Ho<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rible Plot by the Ieſuites, Popiſh Pr<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſts and other Papiſt in the Kingdome of <hi>Ir<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>land,</hi> for the murthering of the two Cheife Iuſtices and all the Priv<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Counſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l and Prote<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tants o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>and,</hi> as alſo to ſe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>z<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> on all the Ki<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gs <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>irs, C<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtles and M<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>en  whatſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er an<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:112371:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 38 -->moreover, that they would murther all perſons that ſhould oppoſe them in any of their inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and deſires, which were theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, to have their Crowne not to bee dependant upon <hi>England,</hi> nor to be a conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Nation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, to have their <hi>Iriſh</hi> Lawes eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, and ſuch as ſhould bee made hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, to have free liberty of the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of their Relegion.</p>
            <p>The Earle of <hi>Leiceſter</hi> declared the ſame al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, adding that hee had the originall of a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation which was made there, and had cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the ſame to bee coppied out. The Letter beares date the twenty third of <hi>October,</hi> 1641. declaring that <hi>Hugh Ocorett</hi> went to <hi>Dublin</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the lodging of <hi>Hugh Maymubawne</hi> his very good friend, and he and his friend going to the lodging of the Lord Marques, underſtood great ſtore of Noble men and ſtrangers had beene there, but they were all gone abroad, and they could not finde them; wherefore they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned backe againe to his friends lodging, where his friend revealed unto him the whole Plot; but ſwore unto him he ſhould not ſtirre till it was put into execution, and therefore his friend commanded his ſervants to looke nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly to him: but after a while he fained ſome excuſe of neceſsity for his going downe, which
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:112371:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 38 -->his friend gave way too, but ſent his ſervants with him: when he was come downe, the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants not being ſo carefull to watch him as they might have beene, he leaped over a wall in the yard, and made an eſcape, and went to Sir <hi>Iohn Burlacy,</hi> and diſcovered to him the whole Plot, which was this.</p>
            <p>That at nine of the Clocke the next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebels (amongſt whom the Lord <hi>Marques</hi> was on of the chiefeſt) intended at one hower and moment of time, to maſſacre and murder all the Engliſh and Proteſtants in the Kingdome of <hi>Ireland,</hi> likewiſe to murder the two Lord chiefe Iuſtices, and all the privy coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell at <hi>Dublin,</hi> and at the ſame time, to ſeaze up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all the Kings Caſtles, Forts, and Magazens throughout the whole Kingdome of <hi>Ireland,</hi> as alſo the Caſtle of <hi>Dublin,</hi> and that if they ſhould finde any of the Citie that would not ſubmit to them, then they would ſhoote downe from the Caſtle, the tops of the Chimnys to affright them, and if that did not prevaile, they would then batter downe their houſes about their cares. Hereupon the Lord chiefe Iuſtice and the reſt of the privy Councell of <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſat all night in conſultation, and tooke the beſt courſe they could immagine of for the ſafeguard &amp; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of themſelves; together with the Caſtle and City of <hi>Dublin.</hi> The next morning they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:112371:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 39 -->great ſtore of theſe Trators and Rebells, together with the Lord <hi>Marquiſe,</hi> who was gone from his lodging before day and hid in a Cockloft, and at his lodging they found great ſtore of Chaines, Hammers, and Hutchets without halves. The ſame day they had notice of ſeverall places and Forts ſeaſed upon in <hi>Conno</hi> and <hi>Monno</hi> and other places, together with ſeverall Villages plundered by the Rebells; but they wrote word that they did not beleeve that diſtemper was ſo generall as was reported to be, and then they made no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion but they ſhould with care and paines bring all to a good iſſue; to that end they had ſent for five hundred of the Horſe to come and guard them at <hi>Dublin,</hi> and had likewiſe raiſe five hundred <hi>Engliſh</hi> for the ſucuring of themſelves and the City, and that out of thoſe five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred they had choſen an hundred to be put into the Caſtle under the command of Sir <hi>Francis Welloughby,</hi> who they hoped would give a good accompt to his Majeſty of the place fees two Monthes: And in the meane time for feare leaſt there ſhould be ſome further and worſer plots then they knew of, they did deſire that the Parliament in <hi>England</hi> would ſend them downe their Lord Lieftenant with m<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, money and Amunition. They further gave
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:112371:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 39 -->us to underſtand, that they had taken order for their Army of old Souldiers, to bee in a readines and to mare in oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to any of the Rebels that ſhould draw to a head.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
